icici bank's managing director and chief
executive officer sandeep bakshi was
chosen as the business standard banker
of the year 20 2021 for turning around
the private sector lender both in terms
of performance and perception during his
tenure of the past three and a half
years a jury of five members chaired by
former rba deputy governor ss mundra
unanimously chose the 61 year old as the
winner
bakshi took charge of india's second
largest private sector lender in october
2018 amid controversy surrounding his
predecessor chanda kochar who had to
step down over corporate governance
issues
only 10 banks qualified under the
criteria used to select the contenders
the jury took into account matters such
as governance recent events hr practices
the regulatory stance innovative
practices and technology prowess to
arrive at a conclusion when the choice
finally came down to two large banks
which had registered strong performance
under both the leaders
ward clinched the decision in favor of
bakshi was turning around the bank after
inheriting a difficult legacy jury chair
ss mundra said bakshi steadied the ship
over the course of the last few years
with a mature leadership while the bank
improved on most of the parameters
bakshi is credited with reviving the
organizational morale also and bringing
in collaborative management leadership
the jury members concurred
the bank rewarded 80 000 frontline
employees with an 8 pay hike during the
covert 19 pandemic year
one of the jury members highlighted that
the turnaround under bakshi was not just
in the banking business but also in the
subsidiaries the banker has been with
icici group since 1986 and handled
assignments across the group in icici
icici lombard general insurance icici
bank and icsa prudential life insurance
he received a two-year extension last
year until october 2023
the media shy business leader who
prefers to keep a low profile accepted
business standards award but declined to
come in further
icsa banks gross and net npas and bad
loan ratios have consistently declined
in the last four years while return on
asset has almost doubled
the bank is well capitalized has strong
ratios adequate provisioning and low bad
loan ratios
for 20 2021 icici bank reported a net
profit of 16193 crore rupees
against 7931 crore rupees in the
preceding financial year
its loan portfolio
grew 13.7 percent year-on-year to 7.34
trillion rupees
while deposits went up by 21
year-on-year
to 9.33 trillion rupees
icc bank shares are up 130 percent in
bakshi's tenure so far under bakshi the
bank is guided by two principles the one
bank one rov principle emphasizes the
need to maximize the bank's share of
profitable growth opportunities across
all products and services whereas the
fair to consumer fair to bank principle
emphasizes the need to deliver fair
value to customers while creating value
for shareholders
on the product side feedback was given
priority over targets which meant that
certain products were withdrawn because
while they were good for the bank they
have not been sold for the clients icac
bank increased its presence rapidly in
the credit card segment too
co-branding and new launches have
boosted credit card sales
its co-branded credit card with amazon
pay has been a huge success in the
market the bank believes leveraging
digital technology is core to its
business its imobile pay app is a
testimony to the bank's execution in
this area
the app has seen 5.3 million activations
from non-icici bank customers
if you like this video share it and
subscribe to business standard for more
news views and insights log on to
www.businesshyphenstandard.com
do also follow us on youtube twitter
facebook instagram telegram and linkedin